UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO SCHOOL OF MEDICINE

Drew E. Winters, PhD.

www.drewEwinters.com drew.winters@cuanschutz.edu 317-525-3133

Biographical sketch

Drew E. Winters, PhD. is a post-doctoral fellow at the University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus In the department of Psychiatry under the Developmental Psychobiology and Behavior T32 program. His research focuses on brain and behavior mechanisms underlying neurocognitive and socio-affective processes with an emphasis on adolescents with callous-unemotional traits. In this vein, this work aims to identify replicable neural mechanisms that may improve development and testing of interventions for youth with callous-unemotional traits.

Education

Edu	cation						
	University of Colorado Anschutz Me	Current					
	- Post-Doctoral Fellow: Develo	pmental Psy	chobiology				
	Research Group (DPRG)						
	- Primary mentor: Dr. Joseph Sakai, M.D.						
	Indiana University, Indianapolis, IN.	– Ph.D.		April 2020			
	Indiana University, Indianapolis, IN. – MSW			May 2016			
	Purdue University, Fort Wayne, IN.			May 2013			
Certifications							
	Machine Learning Using Scikit-Learn in Python – Inira			May 2022			
	Data Scientist in Python - DataCamp			Nov 2021			
	Computational Neuroscience – Neuromatch Academy			July 2021			
	Data Scientist in R – DataCamp			April 2020			
	Multilevel Modeling II Advanced Topics – EITM			Oct 2020			
	Network Analysis II Advanced Topics – EITM			Oct 2020			
	Structural Equation Modeling with Latent Variables – EITM						
Aca	demic appointments						
	University of Colorado	Statistician		2021-2022			
	University of Colorado	Post-Docto	ral Fellow	2020-Present			
	Indiana University	Adjunct Pro	ofessor	2017-2020			
	University of Michigan	Teaching A	ssistant	2019 & 2020			
	Indiana University SOM	Research A	nalyst	2018-2020			
	Indiana University SOM	Research A	ssistant	2016-2020			
	Indiana University	Research A	ssistant	2014-2015			
Hospital, government, or other professional positions							
	UCHealth Encompass program - Au	-	Therapist	2020-2021			
	Family Works Inc Indianapolis, IN		Therapist	2016-2020			
	Rogers behavioral health – Skokie II		Behavioral Therapist	2014-2016			

Honors, special recognitions, and awards

Postdoctoral Association Travel Award

University of Colorado, Aurora, CO		
Empirical Implications of Theoretical Models – Sta	tistics Mastery	2021
Multilevel Modeling II: Advanced Topics		
Empirical Implications of Theoretical Models – Sta	tistics Mastery	2021
Network Analysis II: Advanced Topics	•	
Empirical Implications of Theoretical Models – Sta	tistics Mastery	2018
Structural Equation Modeling with Latent Model	S	
Developmental, Child, and Family Psychology Fell	owship	2018
ICPSR Quantitative Methods of Social Research	Ann Harbor, MI	
Indiana University Travel Fellow		2017-2019
Graduate Professional Student Government Fellows	ship	2016
Miranda Pang Endowment		2014
Phi Kappa Phi: Academic Honor Society		2013
Tau Upsilon Alpha: Human Services Academic Ho	nor Society	2013
Hellen I. and Rodney E. Nern Scholarship		2013
Membership in professional organizations	CD)	2022
Society for the Scientific Study of Psychopathy (SS	2022-current	
Society of Clinical Child and Adolescent Psycholog	gy	2020-current
Society for Social Work and Research (SSWR)		2017-current
Major Committee and Service Responsibilities		
Board of Directors, National Association of Alcoho	l and other Drugs	2011-2018
of Abuse Counselors, Indiana Chapter, Indianapolis		2011-2010
of House counselors, include chapter, includepoins	, 11 (
Licensure and board certification		
<u>License</u>	Certified	Recertified
Licensed Social Worker – Colorado	7/2020	7/2021
Licensed Social Worker – Indiana	7/2016	8/2019
Review and referee work		
Ad Hoc Reviewer		
Translational Psychiatry		2023
Neuroimage		2022
Emotion		2022
Journal of Drug Issues		2022
Addictive Behaviors Reports		2022
Brain Imaging and Behavior		2022
Cerebral Cortex		2021
Neuroscience Letters		2021
Psychophysiology		2021
Journal of Drug and Alcohol Dependence		2021
Journal of Juvenile Justice		2018
Journal of Child and Family Studies		2017
Mindfulness		2016

Open-Source Software Packages

resmod. A python package that derives interaction terms using centered residuals https://pypi.org/project/resmod/, role: author

fsub_extractor. A python package that ties diffusion and functional brain data together.

Invited extramural lectures, presentations and visiting professorships Winters, D.E., Massey, S., Sakai, J. T., Adolescent substance use in response to social consequences of use: The role of empathy. Research Society on Alcoholism, Bellevue, WA.	June 2023
Winters, D.E., Longitudinal Data Analysis Using Secondary Data. S728 multivariate statistics, Dr. Sadaaki Fukui. Indiana University School of Social Work, Indianapolis, IN.	Jan 2023
Winters, D.E., Sakai, J.T., Carter, R.M., Computational Lesioning of Heterogenous Functional Connectomes Explains Variance in Adolescent Callous-Unemotional Traits. Neurohackadamy, University of Washington, Seattle, WA	July 2022
Sanchez, C.R., Cooley, J.L., Winters, D.E. , Ricker, B.T., & Fite, P.J. <i>Prospective associations between forms of aggression and peer victimization: The moderating role of prosocial behavior</i> . Biennial Research Conference on Relational Aggression, Virtual Conference.	July 2022
Winters, D.E. , <i>Introduction to R for medical students</i> . University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, CO	April 2022
Winters, D.E., Cognitive Load Sensitivity Impacts Theory of Mind Impairments in Callous-Unemotional Traits. Developmental Psychobiology Research Group, Denver, CO	April 2022
Winters, D.E., Affective Theory of Mind Impairments in Youth with Callous-Unemotional Traits: The Role of Cognitive Control. American College of Neuropsychopharmacology. San Juan, PR	Dec 2021
Winters, D.E., Network typology of adolescents with callous- unemotional traits. Department of Psychiatry Poster Session, University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, CO	March 2021
Winters, D.E., Adolescent Prosocial Behavior and Affective Theory of Mind: The Role of Cognitive Control and Callousness. Developmental Psychobiology Research Group, Denver, CO	March 2021
Winters, D.E., Longitudinal Data Analysis Using Secondary Data. S728 multivariate statistics, Dr. Sadaaki Fukui. Indiana University School of Social Work, Indianapolis, IN.	Jan 2021
Winters, D.E. , <i>Neural Connectivity of Empathy and its Impairments in Adolescents</i> . Developmental Psychobiology Research Group, Denver, CO	Oct 2020
Winters, D.E. , <i>Statistical Approaches of Propensity Score Matching</i> . Training the Indiana Department of Children Services data analysis and evaluation team, Indianapolis, IN.	March 2020
Winters, D.E., <i>Secondary data analysis</i> . S728 multivariate statistics, Dr. Sadaaki Fukui. Indiana University School of Social Work, Indianapolis, IN.	Jan 2020
Winters, D.E. Mindfulness and Acceptance and Commitment Therapy in Clinical Practice. Advanced clinical practice, Dr. Vincent	June 2017

	Starnino, instructor. Indiana University School of Social Work, Indianapolis, IN.						
	Winters, D.E . <i>Mindfulness in Addictions Treatment</i> . Presentation to staff and clients at the Life Recovery Center, Indianapolis, IN.						
Winter Practic Eta Sig	April 2016						
Teaching record							
	University School of Social Work – Teaching Aractice Research Integrative Seminar	Online	Summer 2017				
	ractice Research Integrative Seminar	Online	Spring 2017				
S623 Pr	ractice Research Integrative Seminar	Seminar	Fall 2016				
Universit	y of Michigan – ICPSR						
Regress	ion Analysis II: Linear models	Online	Summer 2020				
Regress	ion Analysis II: Linear models	Seminar	Summer 2019				
Indiana l	University– Adjunct Professor						
S728 A	dvanced Statistics – Statistics Lab	Seminar	Spring 2020				
	termediate Statistics – Statistics Lab	Seminar	Fall 2019				
	dvanced Statistics – Statistics Lab	Seminar	Spring 2019				
	termediate Statistics – Statistics Lab	Seminar	Fall 2018				
S517 A	ssessment in Mental Health & Addictions	Seminar	Summer 2018				
Mentoring							
Neuron -	2022						
Gabriel	neuroscience track on completing capstone project. Gabriel Yepes, M.D. – Research Mentor						
-							
Grant supp	ort						
Developmental Psychobiology Endowment. Project title: 'Cognitive control limitations amongst adolescents with callous-unemotional traits that impact the capacity for theory of mind: Evidence from a dual-task paradigm.' Funding amount \$7,355 Role: PI			2023 – 2024				
Developmental Psychobiology Endowment. Project title: 'The effects of cognitive load on prosocial behavior amongst early adolescents with high callous-unemotional traits and typically developing controls.' Funding amount \$7,220 Role: PI			2021 – 2022				
National Institutes of Mental Health T32MH015442-42; Laudenslager, Mark (PI), Developmental Psychopathology, Psychobiology & Behavior. <u>Role</u> : Postdoctoral Fellow			2020 – present				
	Department of Children Services Title IV-E Wa CO-0981; Pierce, Barbra (PI), Indiana University		2019 – 2020				

Medicine. Role: Research Analyst

Indiana Department of Children Services Title IV-E Waiver A93-3- 2017 – 2019

13-4F-C0-0981; Hall, Jim (PI), Indiana University School of

Medicine. Role: Research Assistant

Bibliography

Published

Open science legend: * = preregistered; + = analysis code shared; # = data shared

Published Peer-Reviewed Articles

- **Winters, D.E.**, Leopold, D.R., Sakai, J.T., Carter, R.M. (In Press) Resting-state connectivity underlying cognitive control's association with perspective taking in callous-unemotional traits. *Psychiatry Research: Neuroimaging*.
- Winters, D.E., Massey, S., Sakai, J.T., (In Press) Adolescent substance use outcomes in response to social consequences of use: the role of empathy. *Journal of Drug Issues*. DOI: 10.1177/00220426231159303
- *+# Richie-Halford, A., Cieslak, M., Ai, L., Caffarra, S., Covitz, S., Franco, A.R., Karipidis, I.I., Kruper, J., Milham, M., Avelar-Pereira, B., Roy, E., Sydnor, V.J., Yeatman, J.D., The Fibr Community Science Consortium (**Drew E. Winters**), Theodore D. Satterthwaite, Ariel Rokem (2022) An analysis-ready and quality-controlled resource for pediatric brain white-matter research. Scientific Data, 9(1): p. 616.
- + **Winters, D.E.**, Hyde, L. W. (2022). Shared Functional Network Connectivity Between Callous-Unemotionality and both Cognitive and Affective Empathy. *Journal of Affective Disorders*.
- **Winters, D.E.,** Sakai, J.T. (2022) Emotion identification for self and other associated with callous-unemotional traits and sex differences in early adolescents. *Child Psychiatry & Human Development*.
- **Winters, D.E.,** Pruitt P. J., Damoiseaux J.S, Sakai, J.T. (2021). Moderating effect of CU traits on functional connectivity underlying empathy in adolescents. *Psychiatry Research Neuroimaging*. DOI: 10.1016/j.pscychresns.2021.111429
- **Winters D.E.**, Sakai, J.T., Carston, R.M. (2021) Resting-state network topology characterizing callous-unemotional traits in adolescence. Neuroimage: Clinical, 2021: p. 102878.
- **Winters, D.E.,** Susan M., Hopfer, C., Sakai, J.T. (2021). Moderating effects of CU traits on transdiagnostic symptoms association with suicidality in adolescents. *Child Psychiatry and Human Development*. DOI: 10.1007/s10578-021-01256-w
- **Winters D.E.**, Pruitt P. J., Fukui S., Cyders M.A., Pierce B. J., Lay K., Damoiseaux J.S. (2021). Indirect paths between functional connectivity underlying heterogenous depression symptoms in adolescents via cognitive and affective empathy. *Child Psychiatry and Human Development*. DOI: 10.1007/s10578-021-01242-2
- Winters, D.E., Pruit P.J., Fukui, S., Cyders, M. A., Pierce, B. J., Lay, K., Damoiseaux, J. S. (2021). Network functional connectivity underlying dissociable cognitive and affective components of empathy in adolescence. *Neuropsychologia*. DOI: 10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2021.107832
- Winters, D.E., Brandon-Friedman, R., Yepes, G., Hinkley, J. (2020). Systematic review

- and meta-analysis of socio-cognitive and socio-affective processes association with adolescent substance use. *Drug and Alcohol Dependence*. DOI: 10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2020.108479
- **Winters, D.E.**, Pierce, B. J., Imburgia, T. (2020) Concrete services usage on child placement stability: Propensity score matched effects. *Child and Youth Service Review*. DOI: 10.1016/j.childyouth.2020.105362
- **Winters, D.E.**, Wu, W., Fukui, S. (2020). Longitudinal effects of cognitive and affective empathy on adolescent substance use. *Substance Use & Misuse*, 1-7. DOI: 10.1080/10826084.2020.1717537
- Winters, D.E., Fukui, S., Leibenluft, E., Hulvershorn L.A., (2018). Improvements in Irritability with Open-Label Methylphenidate in Youth with Comorbid Attention Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder and Disruptive Mood Dysregulation Disorder. *Journal of Child and Adolescent Psychopharmacology*, 28(5): 298-305.
- Beerbower, E., **Winters, D.E.**, Kondrat, D. (2018). Bio-psycho-social-spiritual needs of adolescents and young adults with life-threatening illnesses: Implications for social work practice. *Social Work in Health Care*, 1-17. DOI: 10.1080/00981389.2018.1430091
- Winters, D.E., Beerbower, E. (2017). Mindfulness and Meditation as an Adjunctive Treatment for Adolescents Involved in the Juvenile Justice System: Is Repairing the Brain and Nervous System Possible? *Social Work in Health Care*, 1-21. Doi:10.1080/00981389.2017.1316341

Published Book Chapters

Armstrong, E., **Winters, D.E.**, Jaggers, J. (2018). Mental Health in Prison Populations. Serving the Stigmatized: Working within the Incarcerated Environment. W.T. Church and D.W. Springer, Oxford University Press.

Technical Reports for the State of Indiana

Winters, D.E., Imburgia, T., Pierce, B. J. (2017, 2018, 2019, 2020). Concrete Services Spending and outcomes for youth. Indiana Department of Child Services Child Welfare Title IV-E Waiver Demonstration Project Extension: Final Report.

Unpublished

Under Review

- *+ Winters, D.E., Leopold, D.R., Sakai, J.T., Carter, R.M. (under review) Efficiency of heterogenous functional connectomes explains variance in callous-unemotional traits after computational lesioning cortical midline and salience regions
- *+ Winters, D.E., Guha A., Sakai, J.T. (under review) Connectome-based predictive modeling of empathy in adolescents with and without the low-prosocial emotion specifier
- *+ Winters, D.E., Sakai, J.T. (under review). Cognitive processes underlying prosocial decision making in callous-unemotional traits.
- + **Winters, D.E.**, Sakai, J.T. (under review). Affective theory of mind impairments underlying callous-unemotional traits and the role of cognitive control: A pilot study.
- **Winters, D.E.**, Sakai, J.T. (under review). Prosocial behavior limitations associated with callous-unemotional traits are moderated by internalizing symptoms
- Sakai, J.T., Chintaluru, Y., Raymond, K., McWilliams, S., Carter, R., Winters, D.E.,

Mikulich, S. (under review). Can Moral Elevation Response Increase Prosocial Behavior? Examining the Effects of Psychopathic Traits.

Winters, D.E., Sakai, J.T. (under review) Callous-Unemotional traits association with prosocial behavior and the mediating role of cognitive control.

In preparation

Winters, D.E., Connectome-based data-driven subgroups association with theoretical groups of callous-unemotional traits and low prosocial emotion specifier